<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>ʿAntaras Mut</title>
                <principal>
                    <persName>Ghassan El-Masri</persName>
                    <persName>Nora Schmidt</persName>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Intertext identifiziert von:</resp>
                    <persName>Toshihiko Izutsu</persName>
                    <name>God and Man in the Quran, Kuala Lumpur 2002, S. 85.</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Webtauglich: nein</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository/>
                        <idno>711</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace>Nağd</origPlace>
                            <origDate>ca. 600 n. Chr. (az-Ziriklī zufolge um 22 vor der Hiğra)</origDate>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
                <bibl type="translation">Ghassan El Masri (vgl. Toshihiko Izutsu, God and Man in the Quran, Kuala Lumpur 2002, S. 85.), Nora Schmidt</bibl>
                <bibl>
                    <edition>ʿAbd al-Raʾūf (Hg.), Dīwān ʿAntara, Cairo o. J.; Ḫalīl al-Ḫūrī (Hg.), Dīwān ʿAntara, Beirut 1893, S. 40.</edition>
                    <relatedItem>
                        <bibl>002:003; 002:033; 003:044; 003:179; 004:034; 004:179; 005:094; 005:109; 005:116; 006:050; 006:059; 006:073; 007:007; 007:188; 009:078; 009:094; 009:105; 010:020; 010:031; 011:049; 011:123; 012:052; 012:081; 012:102; 013:009; 016:077; 018:022; 018:026; 019:061; 019:078; 021:049; 023:092; 027:065; 032:006; 034:003; 034:014; 034:048; 034:053; 035:018; 035:038; 036:011; 039:046; 049:018; 050:033; 052:041; 053:035; 057:025; 059:022; 062:008; 064:018; 067:012; 068:047; 072:026; 081:024</bibl>
                    </relatedItem>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="">
                    <term>
                        <hi xml:lang="ar-Latn"> al-ġaib </hi>
                    </term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <tagsDecl/>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <group>
            <text type="note">
                <body>
                    <p>Die oben angegebenen Belegstellen im Koran beziehen sich auf alle Gebräuche des Substantivs <hi xml:lang="ar-Latn">ġaib</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Izutsu weist darauf hin, dass eine Unterscheidung von "verborgenem" und "offenkundigem" Wissen bzw. "sichtbarer" und "unsichtbarer" Welt im Vorislam getroffen wurde. Der Mensch, der sich ausschließlich in der ihm epistemisch zugänglichen Welt bewegen und orientieren könne, stehe dem Bereich des Unwissbaren ohnmächtig gegenüber. Unwissbar ist für den Menschen, wie im Gedicht ʿAntaras, zum Beispiel die Zukunft.</p>
                    <p>Aber auch Objekte und Ereignisse, die von den menschlichen Sinnen nicht wahrgenommen werden oder durch Hindernisse verstellt sind werden als Teil des <hi xml:lang="ar-Latn">ġaib</hi> wahrgenommen. Die Konnotation der unwissbaren Zukunft wird im Koran im Kontext der Unberechenbarkeit des eschatologischen Gerichts aufgegriffen. Indem Gott als der Besitzer der Schlüssel zum Unwissbaren (<hi xml:lang="ar-Latn">miftaḥ al-ġaib</hi>) vorgestellt wird, erfährt die Kontrastierung von sichtbarer und unsichtbarer Welt jedoch eine entscheidende Veränderung. Statt einer Herausforderung der ihm epistemisch unzugänglichen "Welt" ist der Mensch zu Demut angehalten.</p>
                    <p> </p>
                    <p>Izutsu takes the verse as proof that “the words … ghayb and shahāda in the sense of ‘the invisible’ and ‘the visible’ respectively, were not in any way unknown to the pre-Islamic Arabs”; that they knew and used these notions. Although this is quite possible, the context of the verses leaves no doubt that the verse which Izutsu took is probably Islamic, for the language used is too religious to be the authentic work of a pre-Islamic poet; and this becomes quite clear if one looks at the verse following the verse in question: it fits squarely in <hi xml:lang="ar-Latn">madīḥ ar-rasūl</hi> genre and jars with the genre of heroic poetry to which ʿAntara's work belongs. Izutsu reads the Arabic rasm عالم with the <hi xml:lang="ar-Latn">fatḥa</hi> (<hi xml:lang="ar-Latn">ʿālam al-ghayb</hi>: 'world of the unknown') but if one takes into account our remarks above, combined with the fact that <hi xml:lang="ar-Latn">qadar</hi> is mentioned in the first hemistich as well as 'God's predetermined command' in the poem's opening verse (<hi xml:lang="ar-Latn">ʾamru llāhi ... yuqdaru</hi>), then it would make better sense to read the rasm following the qur'anic <hi xml:lang="ar-Latn">ʿālim al-ghayb</hi>: 'He who knows the unknown', viz. God.<lb/>It should be noted that there are a priori considerations that render suspect all but very cautious use of ʿAntara's poetry as a source on the practices (linguistic or otherwise) of the pre-Islamic Arabs. Although a rich and sizeable Dīwān is attributed to ʿAntara, only fragments of his poetry survived in the primary source anthologies and early collections: Ibn Salām al-Jumaḥī’s counted him among <hi xml:lang="ar-Latn">shuʿarāʾ al-wāḥida</hi> (poets that produced only one poem), and Ibn Al-Mubārak in his Muntaha aṭ-Ṭalab cites only five of his poems/fragments, yet tens of integral poems are ascribed to him in the different editions of his dīwāns. Apart from what has been written by Margoliouth and Ṭaha Ḥusayn on the matter of the authenticity of pre-Islamic poems, a thorough study of ʿAntara’s poetry can be found in Fawzī Muḥammad Amīn, ʿAntara b. Shaddād al-ʿAbsī, (Palestine, Dār al-Maʿrifa al-Jāmiʿiyya, 2004) and in Khūrī’s introduction to his Dīwān.</p>
                    <p>Vgl. auch Intertext Nr. 712.</p>
                </body>
            </text>
            <text xml:lang="ar-Arab" type="orig">
                <body>
                    <p>دعوني أجدُّ السَّعي في طلب العُلا  فأُدْرِكَ سُؤْلي أو أمُوتَ فأُعذَرُ<lb/>ولاَ تختشوا مما يقدرُ في غدٍ  فما جاءَنا منْ <hi rendition="bold">عالم الغيبِ</hi> مخبرُ<lb/>وكمْ منْ نَذِيرٍ قدْ أَتَانا محذِّراً  فكانَ رسولاً في السُّرور يبَشّر</p>
                </body>
            </text>
            <text xml:lang="deu-Latn">
                <body>
                    <p>Lasst mich die Anstrengung des Strebens nach Ruhm antreten,     denn entweder siege ich, oder ich sterbe und bin vergeben.   Und fürchtet euch nicht davor, was für morgen verheißen ist,      denn aus der Welt des Unwissbaren haben wir keine Kunde.     Wie viele Warner kamen zu uns mit Bangen     und wurden zu Botschaftern, die freudig das Glück verkünden.</p>
                </body>
            </text>
            <text xml:lang="eng-Latn">
                <body>
                    <p>Let me take the pains of the pursuit of glory   for either I attain my goal or be excused [if I fail]<lb/>And fear not for what has been predestined for tomorrow   for nobody has ever brought us any news from the <hi rendition="bold">world of the unseen</hi>
                        <lb/>And how many forewarner came to us with alarms   but then he became a messenger of joy giving us the good tidings</p>
                </body>
            </text>
        </group>
    </text>
</TEI>